Okay, hello.
Look at this beautiful web page.
So I'm going to be talking about tracks.
What are tracks?
Tracks are an HTML element that you can put
inside of an audio tag,
like inside the beginning tag and the closing tag of
audio or video.
I don't think it goes in any other ones,
but it's possible.
In this case,
I have a video tag that is loading 8 megabyte track.
Somebody compressed the movie
Shrek to
a little bit over 8 megabytes.
More than half of that is actually the audio compressed
in a format called Opus,
which is a free and open source and a royalty free codec.
There
aren't
all that many that are all those things at once.
And Opus is special because it has technology
that is really good at encoding speech
and also quite good at encoding music.
And it can,
it has
some logic where it's able to detect to detect
when the sound is speech or music and then kind
of pivot between those modes.
So it can be really effective for
making large files into small files.
And if you're trying to make a file
that's smaller than nine megabytes,
like the discord file attachment limit or what it used to be,
then that kind of thing can be really useful.
In addition to the video tag on this page.
And we'll look at the code.
There's also a track.
I downloaded an SRT file off of one of those
sites where you just search for like Shrek SRT.
And it took two or three to find one that was actually in
sync with the movie because there's different versions from
DVD rips and blue day blue ray rips and streaming versions.
But this one seems to work.
I need to fix this.
So it actually shows that this is like the English subtitles here.
Also this details tag that I unintentionally toggled,
which shows the transcript.
And that's because of code that I wrote that looks at the.
Time text that's available to the browser
and then Q by Q. Adds it to this div.
This div has its own scroll bar.
And I've as I'm adding these lines of text to the div.
I'm also adding as data attributes,
which is you can like a tag will have its own attributes that,
you know,
like
a tags have SRC.
Like HRTF
image tags have SRC canvas tags have with
the night because as that kind of image,
they don't.
Not like they don't come in with their own coordinate system.
You can also add arbitrary tags to any element.
But they have to be propended with like data dash.
So you can get data dash,
you know,
whatever you want and store stuff in that.
So I'm in these tags.
I'm storing.
The start time and end time of each tag.
And I'm using that
to highlight the.
The active part of the transcript.
So. Looking at the transcript here.
Let's go straight to somebody once
told me the world is going to roll me.
If I click this, it'll take us there.
As you can tell,
there's,
you know,
a lot of a lot of quality.
This is.
Like really high resolution.
Beautiful image.
This is I max.
You can also see that the track element is doing what we expect.
It's showing the text overlaid on top of the video.
It has a dark background to create contrast on top of the white text.
And something else that's happening here because
of code I wrote and code that we will look at.
It is.
It's highlighting the active queue in this div.
And if we let this run,
we will also see that it scrolls to that.
So. Oh, if I, if I check this.
It's a little bit out of sync.
But what can you do?
So I have this, this.
I put element here,
which is a check box.
And if it's checked,
whatever
the active closed caption will be will
both be bold and purple dark purple,
I think.
And it will always be the top element of the div.
But if you uncheck this,
it stops scrolling.
So you see they'll just light up.
Feels like a karaoke player, right?
Sort of feels an instrumental version maybe.
God, I don't like that song at all.
So that's, that's plenty, right?
Like let's look at the code now.
We have some basic HTML stuff going on here that should be familiar.
Type language,
head style.
The video is 80. 80% of the viewport,
which is,
you know,
significant width,
but not so much to take up the entire screen.
I have this MF class that I'm using in the,
in the transcript viewer for the emphasize text.
I could have overloaded.
Strong or one of the other tags,
but I decided to just use a class for this.
So it's bold and dark orchid.
The transcript div use.
So it's seeing if the.
It is a maximum height.
It has a font size.
And if the height of the contents of that
element are more than 300 on the while element,
which is the height,
you know,
beyond the height,
it adds a scroll bar.
That's how easy it is to do that.
Also,
a mad with max width of 700 pixels and a box shadow,
which could be blurrier,
actually.
But you
can see the pop up here.
So
it doesn't actually say what the values are.
Anyway,
one of these is how much it blurs and what color.
We move into the body.
We have our video tag with 8 megabyte track.
We have the VTT file for the time text.
I have
the input, which I'm calling please scroll.
It is the checkbox and it has this text
in the H3 element.
Then I'm bringing in this.
Transcript JS,
which is code I wrote and what you're happy you're welcome to use.
Happy.
I don't think you'll be happy to use it,
but you are welcome to use it.
And then I'm just setting some variables to point at these
different DOM elements so I can access them in the code.
We got please scroll points at the.
The checkbox track is actually.
Track is not a DOM object.
It's looking at the video.
And then.
The video text track zero is it's a
different kind of object than that.
If I were to just do a query selector for track.
You can use.
I believe you can use the same event listeners
on the track object versus the DOM thing,
but they're.
They also differ in some ways.
And it's just like.
I feel like some of you are probably going like what?
But this is why you refer to documentation.
Every time I work with this stuff,
I have to go to MDN and be like.
Oh,
like what?
What what methods are available to the track object?
The track DOM object versus like
the text track kind of like
object thing.
And that's just,
you know,
no one expects you to memorize all this stuff.
And you'll get better at.
Remembering where to look.
I have some reference here to the Q change event.
And so the Q change event is something
you can put an event listener on.
And it's every time.
The text for the closed caption changes.
I think that's a good thing to be able to look at,
right?
Only one Q should be active at a time because that's the way that.
Close captions work, right?
It's not all like the.
The underlying code API is actually allow for multiple.
Cues to be active at a time though.
So maybe that's the basis of a cool art project
where you can have like lots of time text at once.
But.
For the sake of eight megabyte track,
I'm just loading the first one.
And if that,
if there's actually something there.
Because when I was testing,
sometimes they were empty.
And then my like I'd get an error.
Nothing would work.
So I had this if as a test.
And if there's anything there,
this will resolve us true.
And the if will function.
So it's I am matching the data start.
I mentioned that I'm like storing
the start time actually in the divs.
And. The way that looks in the element going back here,
going into our dev tools,
if we actually look at one of these.
It's like div data start is this many seconds data.
And is this many seconds data index,
which I'm not actually using.
But it's good to know.
I also have this title.
So when you roll over this,
it shows you the start time.
And hours minute seconds.
And then it has the actual.
Text value in the div.
So as I said, it's like
any attribute you want, propended by data.
But when you're accessing it in JavaScript,
you you you access it through data set.
So data dash start is the same thing
as that div.com object.data set.start.
So you can read them and write them by accessing this data set.
So.
In terms of like a queue object, and
I'm actually going to like show you.
This documentary, this documentation page.
Is like here we get this queue change.
You get an array of active cues.
And what a queue is.
Is one of these.
Where it has a line,
it has these like options of snap to line.
But the main the important things for us
is that they have start time and time.
Right.
Oh, it's text track queue.
And
the start time and end time capitalized like that.
And they also have this like pause on exit.
Like that's something that you could write code around.
So I'm using the start time and end time here to
compare against the what stored in the data set.
To scroll into view and add that class
to make it purple.
And so this is actually just a really simple.
loop here.
That's looping through all of the divs looking
at these data attributes that I stored them in in
this other chunk of code called transcript JS,
which you're welcome to use.
And I'll walk through after this.
To to do that that interface where it's making the purple,
it's scrolling to them.
And if please scroll dot checked.
And so on a input element, that is a
check box.
Checked will be true if it's checked and false of it isn't.
It's updated automatically.
You can add also how to vent listeners to check boxes.
But I don't even need to use one in this case.
Scrolling to view is just a native HTML. Like
native JavaScript function for any HTML element.
You can do it whenever you want.
You could you could make some pretty
fun stuff by having a very long page and
scrolling different objects to view.
Using a timed element.
That can be a fun project.
So if out of all of the like hundreds and hundreds of divs,
each one of which is storing one line of
text from this hour and a half long movie.
If it matches that one gets
the M class.
And if it if it doesn't match.
So it's actually looping through every single transcript.
It may not be the best way to do it.
But every other one is having the class.
So there's probably more efficient ways to do it.
But it works.
So that's nice.
And I'm going to go through this transcript.js code.
I don't expect to hold this to make sense to you.
But I'm going to do it just for the sake of you having the reference.
And maybe also for me to remember like what I did.
So I'm loading all of the track DOM elements into the text.
It is TRKS variable.
I've got some helper functions here.
Sleep returns a promise after so many milliseconds.
HMS is not her majesty service.
It is hours minute seconds.
So it'll take.
You know, if you have
most of the things that deal with the timeline that deal with
duration that deal with current time are measured in seconds.
You know, they can have
decimal points after them.
That's fine.
But it's hard to think in time that way. So
if you if you input like 1500 seconds here,
it will turn that into so many minutes and so many seconds.
So I was running into this issue where yes,
the video had loaded.
And I actually wrote this to deal with.
Multiple tracks being on the page.
I wrote this actually for the the page that I
originally wrote transcript.js for the page.
I'm putting these video tutorials on where there's
several video files and each one has its own transcript.
But
it was hard for me to detect when they'd all loaded.
And this is not the most efficient way to do this.
But
for each of the tracks,
it checks to see if it's ready state
is to.
Which means it's loaded.
If it hasn't,
it waits three seconds and tries again.
I was trying to listen to the loaded or load event listener.
And for some reason,
it wasn't firing in a reliable way.
And this worked.
I probably was doing something wrong
in the way that I. Had set that up.
But
sometimes you just need like a
quick and dirty solution rather than.
So this is a fairly like best practices
that came up at the colloquium this week.
Best practices can be a trap.
So this function is saying like if it's not ready,
wait three seconds.
And what it actually does is it calls the same function again.
We call this a recursive function because it calls itself.
And so this will just keep calling itself every every three
minutes until all of the ready states on the tracks are loaded.
And then it returns true.
So we have another do the thing here,
which is just usually what I call my.
My function that's like waiting for
something to happen and then going.
So it's waiting for this track check to happen.
And then it process the tracks.
Processing the tracks.
Is running a loop on all of the video elements on a page.
It's loading the first text track for each video.
Here into track.
It's creating an element a details element.
It's creating a summary inside the details element.
You know, I feel like.
There's a version of this where I fixed because
it's saying it said details on the page.
We looked at instead of transcript because I
didn't I'm not actually adding this summary.
To. Yeah, I'm not actually adding this.
I'm just going to start debugging in real
time context content equals transcript.
That's the details thing.
That makes sense.
And then.
I'm just staring into space.
Now I'm just going to keep going Slow.
I will put the updated version in the in the source code.
And if you can like check the diff file.
Okay.
But basically, like, I'm going to get the data.
This summary is get this transcript text
content is getting overloaded or something.
Added some console log messages for diagnostic purposes.
I was debugging.
You don't have to worry about those.
We've got text track zero being loaded into this variable,
which is the same thing as track.
I don't think I actually end up using track.
I end up using TT. I've got an array of all of the time.
Text.
If there is no length to this text track,
it means there's no cues.
The length of cues.
So the cues is going to be an array of
all of the text in this track element.
So if there aren't any cues,
it throws an error and ends the program.
If there are cues,
it copies them into this array.
Call it CTR. And then.
We have this this loop,
this for loop.
Running on TTR entries.
This is this is kind of a goofy way to do a four
of loop while still getting access to the iterator.
But anyway,
for each entry,
it's creating a paragraph tag.
No,
it was a paragraph tag,
but I ended up using a div,
even though it stored in a variable called P. It's.
Also creating an H3. The H3's text content is set to the time stamp.
We append that.
Outside of the loop,
I have this variable that's storing the last time.
So we're doing some math here to figure out.
How long it's been between captions.
We add this click event to the each paragraph.
To move to the video.
To the data set start.
We're setting text the P text content here,
which is actually erasing this operation,
because I decided I didn't want the time stamps in every line.
To. The Q text with some replacement pattern
replacement going on here to remove HTML. And then.
The transcript appends the div with all the text in it.
And then.
This is a little.
Some logic here that will add like silence.
How many seconds of silence appear in the in the thing?
And there's a couple examples of that if we go back to tracks here.
Yeah,
so there's like 10 seconds of silence
here after only shooting stars break the.
I wish I wish it was just an hour and a half of silence to be honest.
But that's that's all that's going on in transcript.js.
It's generating all of these HTML tags
to show the transcript for each video file.
And again, I don't expect you to totally rock.
However,
this because this is this is like fever code.
I was writing this on sleep deprivation.
And. When I was sick at the beginning in the morning.
And so I'm kind of looking at I'm like,
why did I?
Why did I do this?
Why did I do it this way?
Why did I use this kind of loop?
This is goofy.
Like this is this is bad pedagogy.
And I hope most of you have stopped.
Watching this tutorial like
five minutes ago.
But that's that's how you work with tracks.
That's how you work with tracks.